275 Hawthorne Ave Apt 133, Palo Alto, CA 94301 (520) 869-6384 — joe@sortelli.com — https://github.com/sortelli/

PROFILE

Fullstack software engineer with 12+ years of experience in delivering on-time solutions that meet critical business needs. Possesses an advanced technical background and is an enthusiastic mentor to other engineers. Lifelong learner and passionate practitioner of software engineering best practices.

SKILLS

- Advanced experience with frontend and backend programming in many languages, including with C, Java, Javascript, Ruby, and Python. Familiarity with many others.
- Familiar with modern web application stacks, built on open source components such as AngularJS, Express, Node.js, Rails, Spring and more. Learns new stacks and codebases very quickly.
- Specialized focus in build systems and build tools, including advanced knowledge of git, Gradle, Gulp, Maven, SBT and many others. Passionate about improving the overall developer experience through best practices and better tooling.
- Experienced in advanced UNIX programming topics, including interprocess communication, network programming, memory management, process control, optimization and dynamic linking.
- Experienced in semantic web programming, ontological reasoning, and linked data application development. Worked with RDF, SPARQL, SWRL, SPIN, RDFS, and OWL.

EXPERIENCE

- Managed multiple engineering teams with up to eight direct reports at a time. Experienced leader and mentor, with a strong product management sense.
- Worked closely with internal customers to create many small and large sized products and tools that address critical business needs.
- Created a two way SSL based encryption layer for Elasticsearch. This fork requires a client certificate for all node-to-node and HTTP endpoint communication.

 Available at https://github.com/sortelli/elasticsearch.
- Created plugins and tools for eclipse, jenkins, gradle, Bamboo, Stash and many other systems.
- Created a Ruby based framework on top of the C API of RMS PDM, and integrated a Ruby interpreter into the application daemon to create a framework for plugin development.
- Designed and built a semantic enterprise business data analysis platform, using Hadoop for distributed RDF generation of large datasets, and rule based inferencing. Created a SPARQL integration for Elasticsearch, to enable a faceted full text search capability for the backend triple store.

WORK HISTORY

Palantir Technologies

Internal Applications Developer
May 2014 - Present

Palo Alto, CA.

Senior fullstack engineer on the Internal Applications team, responsible for building internally focused products to help Palantir scale.

Performed a major system migration from various legacy backend systems to an off-the-shelf enterprise HRIS system. Advised and mentored other engineers on engineering best practices, including starting a culture of code review and automated testing.

Palantir Technologies

 $Internal\ Tools\ Team\ Lead$

Palo Alto, CA.

May 2013 - May 2014

Led the Internal Tools team at Palantir, which is responsible for the builds and build systems across the organization.

Moved Palantir from a small monolithic home-grown build system to one based on open source tools. Increased the scale of operations of the build team from supporting a single group of product engineers to supporting all the engineers at the company.

Transitioned the team from supporting hand-maintained servers to using Puppet to efficiently manage hundreds of build servers.

Palantir Technologies

DeltaWorks Team Lead

Palo Alto, CA.

January 2013 - May 2013

Co-led team of Forward Deployed Software Engineers, named DeltaWorks. DeltaWorks is an off-cycle product engineering developer group responsible for writing customer focused products to be used on the front lines by our Business Development Forward Deployed Engineers.

Palantir Technologies

Forward Deployed Software Engineer

Palo Alto, CA.

May 2012 – January 2013

Forward Deployed Software Engineer on the DeltaWorks team. Transitioned all the Business Development (BD) engineers from using a small SBT based build system to properly leveraging Gradle for a better developer experience.

Wrote and maintained BD product code for Palantir Gotham, Palantir's flagship product. Trained BD new-hires during the company on-boarding process on how to be effective Forward Deployed Engineers.

Raytheon Missile Systems

Multi-Disciplined Engineer

Tucson, AZ.

June 2003 - May 2012

Member of Raytheon Missile Systems' Engineering Productivity Enhancement Team, and lead architect of the Raytheon Exchange semantic business data analytics tool.

Previously the chief programmer and developer team lead for RMS PDM, a multi-business product data management and configuration control database system. Worked directly with customers to continuously improve the functionality and capabilities of the system.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science, Computer Science University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ

December 2007

Minors in Computer Engineering and Math.